<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second vindication of the magistracy and government of England by way of an answer to the several replies &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Shower, Bartholomew, Sir, 1658-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37550</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16971900</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16971900</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105562</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60124)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105562)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1159:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second vindication of the magistracy and government of England by way of an answer to the several replies &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Shower, Bartholomew, Sir, 1658-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints to Sir Bartholomew Shower.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rye House Plot, 1683.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  1660-1714.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105562:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SECOND VINDICATION OF THE Magiſtracy and Government OF ENGLAND, By way of ANSWER to the ſeveral REPLIES, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is very obſervable, that ſince the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution, nothing hath more diſturbed our Peace than the Liberty of the Preſs: and amongſt all our new Prints, the moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant and miſchievous Libels on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government have been written by thoſe Lawyers who pretend themſelves the greateſt Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots for its Honor and Service; which may be ſuſpected as falſe, unleſs it be withal conſidered, that ſome modern Royalliſts have nothing recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatory of themſelves but the miſcarriages of others; and others of them have ſuch great ones of their own, that an extenuation or excuſe is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, and therefore to cloud their own Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities they would blacken other Mens Reputations, and in order to it they have cenſured Innocence, and arraigned Laws; and where a ſlip or fault hath been, tho ſo ſmall as ſcarcely to deſerve the name of one, they have magnified it into an exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Villany; and for a colour of ſuch their Calumny and Slander, they have vented new Goſpel and Law both: nay they have broached ſuch Notions to the World, as are directly fatal to that Crown of which they boaſt themſelves the Makers and Supporters, and yet in doing ſo they pretend to merit—</p>
            <p>It is ſtrange but true, for the Fact is plain, and the Conſequence too: upon the preſent Change, the Republicans of both Gowns, did deem it their Policy and Intereſt to beſpatter and reproach other Mens Actions; and like baſe and mean ſpirits, gave ill Names and Words to every thing in which themſelves had not been concerned, and made reviling ſo cuſtomary, that it is become the modiſh ſin of the Age. It is moſt certain the old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Honor, Frankneſs, Ingenuity, and good Nature, is quite abandoned from ſome Companies and Places in the Town, and inſtead of Folly, we have aſſumed a vice in our common Converſation, inſtead of Drollery and Banter, the new faſhioned Wit at — <hi>'s</hi> allows nothing as acceptable but Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Slander; nay the very Spark of a Courtier hath changed his note, whereas fulſom, groſs, and falſe Flattery was wont to be his Talent, he is now got to the other extreme, <hi>i.e.</hi> revengeful, weak, and falſe Characters, both of Perſons and Actions. Which is the worſt is difficult to determine, but falſhood is the moſt predominant humor in both, and that Age is ſurely unhappy which is plagued with a Surfeit of either, eſpecially when the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs is ſo great as now, that no Gentleman can be thought a good Companion, no Clergyman a true Proteſtant, no Lawyer an honeſt <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> no Courtier a faithful Servant, unleſs he can, and do Rail, and Snarl, and Scold, and that at things that were juſtly uſed in former times, and muſt neceſſarily be uſed in theſe times, and will be ſo in all times whatſoever, even in <hi>Secula Seculorum.</hi> Theſe little ſtinging Animals do value themſelves upon their Honeſty, becauſe they find Faults, but it is in caſes where no Eye can ſpie them but their own; they value themſelves upon their Wit, becauſe their cenſures are ſharp and biting, but that is ſo eaſie, ſo very eaſie a Province, that Nature teaches even the rudeſt of her breed to be Satyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and the Natural oftentimes outdoes the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Scholar in Rib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ldry, and hath perhaps a better faculty that way for fancy and piquancy of reflection.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105562:2"/>
            <p>Now as the Fact is thus Criminal and Ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous both, ſo muſt the Conſequence prove fatal to the Government which they would be thought (but intend not) to ſupport, for when once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to Arraign all paſt proceedings, they are forced for the maintenance of ſuch their Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to vent thoſe Opinions, Doctrines, and Rules in Divinity and Law, which have in every Age (ſave one) been juſtly exploded as deſtructive to the honor and being of the then Poſſeſſors of the Crown; and can conduce to no other end than the utter Subverſion of this, and every other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment that doth but ſmell of a Monarchy.</p>
            <p>It cannot be denied but in moſt Reigns there have been ſome occaſions given for diſguſt to the People, that Kings have born too hard upon their Subjects, that the Subjects have worthily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of ſome Warps from the Law; but no Man ever with Senſe pretended that this is a reaſon to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a belief, that every Act of State, and every Judgment of Law in former times was Arbitrary and unwarrantable: no ſurely, the Publiſhers of ſuch Reflections are of another thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and ſome folks imagine, they who formerly were ingaged in Seditious Practices againſt the Crown, would now upon the preſent occaſion explode that Law which doth condemn ſuch Practices, that they may with impunity repeat them whenſoever the King or his Miniſters ſhall chance to diſoblige them, and that this is the true reaſon of half the new Libels and invectives upon paſt Proceedings.</p>
            <p>It is now apparent to all Mankind, that every Line, or at leaſt Page, of ſome Mens Works are deſigned only as a Courtſhip to the Mobb, by bridling the Sovereignty, and clipping the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, even to ſuch a degree, as doth abſolutely deprive it of thoſe Rights, Powers, and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which the ancient Law, continued Uſage, and our preſent Repreſentatives conſent to allow it.</p>
            <p>To check this growing itch of Pamphleting the Nation into another Change, and to vindicate the Rights of the Crown, and juſtifie the Magiſtracy of <hi>England</hi> from the obloquy which was indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly thrown on it in one Particular: there was three months ſince, a Sheet Printed and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, at which ſome Men took offence, but others were of Opinion, that its Publication was ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and well timed; that its reflection on the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling Defence which it aſſumed to anſwer, were juſt and ſmooth, and very ſoft, conſidering the occaſion given for a more Satyrical Stile from the fondneſs and incoherence of the Defenders expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and inferences, and that the mode of managing his Argument, was modeſt and tender, with a decent and due regard to the memory of the unfortunate deceaſed, which had ſuffered more than enough of Injury by that pretended Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>A Cholerick and Sedulous Enquiry hath been made after the Authors Name, but the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor is ſtill at a loſs, notwithſtanding his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of a certain knowledg who it was that came behind and ſtruck him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But to give him ſome ſatisfaction, after all his fatigue in ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I will aſcertain who it was not; he may aſſure himſelf that none concerned in that Tryal, were concerned or privy to its Vindication, and when it was Compoſed and Writ, the Party in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it chiefly for his own and the worlds di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, from the ungrateful neceſſity of Reading always on one ſide, by the interpoſal of a few Lines on the other; that our Humors might not be quite ſowned, and our Genius turn too peviſh through the influence of Satyr and Libel, with which the World hath too much abounded of late years; nor had there been one word more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed upon that Subject, but that the Authority of the Defender doth challenge a Vindication, and the word of a Prieſt ſays that it needs one; both ſhall have an anſwer preſently.</p>
            <p>But firſt it is remarkable, that this new Reply hath got a Licenſe, when none of his other ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate Works could procure one, however it is poſſible that the Licenſer may hereafter renounce, or retract his Allowance in this caſe, as he hath done in ſeveral others already, when his Superiours are acquainted with the Contents and Tendencies of that to which he hath given his <hi>Imprimatur;</hi> for it is not to be ſuppoſed, that Miniſters of State will ever be ſo incurious of their Maſters Honor, and the Rights of his Crown, as to approve their diminution, when once they perceive it.</p>
            <p>The ſingle Point which the Advocate for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy aſſumed to maintain, was that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment in queſtion was Legal and Good, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient both for matter and form, and did warrant the Judgment which was pronounced upon the Verdict that affirmed its truth. This ſeems the principal Aſſertion in that Paper, which whether his Preſidents and Authorities, Arguments and Reaſons, are ſufficient to prove, the Reader muſt judge. That the Caſes he cites are truly reported for ſo much as he uſes them, none can deny, and that the Law is with him upon the whole matter, ſhall be further evinced.</p>
            <p>But ſince that Sheet hath made ſome noiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt angry Men (which was little expected by him that wrote it) it will not I hope be thought impertinent to ſpend a few Paragraphs upon the boiſterous and bluſtering invectives and remarks made againſt its Author in a pretended Reply. In his Vindication therefore I ſhall obſerve, the Temper, the Wit, the Gueſs, the Reaſon, the Religion, and laſtly the Law of that Replication.</p>
            <p>As to the Temper it ſeems to be writ under ſome diſappointment, for the Author doth in every Sentence declare his Paſſion, and plainly tells us that he was then diſcompoſed, but whether his diſpleaſure were conceived at a paſt or preſent Chief is not ſo eaſie to determine: to expoſe his fury, it is enough to repeat his Epithets of Daring, Bold, Impudent, Preſumptuous, Baſe, Ingenerous, Inſolent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all this deſpiſed by his reputed Author, and ſmiled at by the real one. He is pleaſed to call the Sentence and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution a plain Murder, which if ſo, ſure I am that he is bound in Conſcience to Proſecute an
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105562:2"/>Indictment againſt the Judges, the Recorder, the Grand and the Petit Jury, the Witneſſes, the Clerks, the Sollicitors, the Goaler, the Sheriffs, and the Executioner, for they were all concerned either as Acceſſories, or Principals, and demerit a Halter if the Repliants Opinion be Law; but it is obſerved amongſt <hi>Honeſt Men</hi> that none of theſe Parties ſhew any fear on't, and the reaſon they give for it is, becauſe the Indictment was as good as their Juriſdiction, and the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of thoſe two makes them as ſafe as an Act of Indempnity can do: but all this was Paſſion.</p>
            <p>As to the Wit on't moſt of his Readers are at a loſs where to find it, unleſs it be in his <hi>Engliſh</hi> Verſes, which do ſo hit the ſenſe of the Original, and contain ſuch ſtrong and pregnant flights of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Poetry, that ſome of his Readers have compared them even with <hi>Sternhold</hi> and <hi>Hopkins,</hi> and others are of Opinion that they do not come ſhort of the Eſſays of the two <hi>Grays-Inn</hi> Poets, one of which Tranſlated <hi>Grotius, de Veritate Chriſtianae Religionis,</hi> and the other <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton</hi> into Rhime, but the generality do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that for height of Fancy, Propriety of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> and exactneſs of Rhime he hath much out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done all thoſe: but for my part I believe that laſt Rhapſody was added not ſo much for the Ingeny ſake, as to menace the Anſwerer with a deſign to Sacrifice him whenſoever an occaſion ſhould offer it ſelf, and conſequently to do what the whole Book complains of; but that Advocate is not ſo much a Coward as to be afraid on't.</p>
            <p>As for the Gueſs, it is very cunning, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues more Figure Knowledg than true Judgment in Styles, Modes, Dialects, or Peculiarities of Speech, or Writing, for he will have the Author of that Sheet, to be the Author of the <hi>Antidote,</hi> though he never ſaw it till he had the misfortune to have read the <hi>Defence;</hi> and his particular Idioms are as different from thoſe of the <hi>Antidote,</hi> as they are from thoſe of the <hi>Defence;</hi> but this is all gueſs. He will have it one of the Council of that Tryal, becauſe he hath put <hi>Council</hi> before <hi>Court:</hi> a Cunning Man would have gueſs'd the contrary, as ſuppoſing it done <hi>fallendi gratia,</hi> for the ſake of diſguiſe; but he may be aſſured it was mere accident that occaſioned that fault. He will have it to be the then Sollicitor, becauſe of his Reputation, which is ſuppoſed to be touched in that <hi>Defence:</hi> but his Readers think that that Gentlemans Figure for Learning, Honor, and Vertue is ſo far above the reach of a little Pamphlet, that all the virulent Reproaches of the <hi>Reply</hi> cannot Sully it, nor is it in the power of any Tongue or Pen to prejudice his Character in the World; but however it is prudent to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to my ſelf an eminent Adverſary, that if a Foil be my fortune, it may be the eaſier.</p>
            <p>But ſince we are at gueſſing, the World gueſſes that he who wrote the <hi>Reply,</hi> did write the half Sheet called the <hi>Juſtification;</hi> and it is really ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to read the <hi>Juſtifier,</hi> commending the <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> for a learned worthy Perſon; and the <hi>Repliant</hi> doing the ſame good Office for the <hi>Juſtifier,</hi> and almoſt in the ſame words commending him: nay he ſpends an whole Page in the moſt fulſom praiſes upon that <hi>Small Bulk</hi> Author, and rejoyces that the Work was done to his Hands, which is a very pretty jeſt. It is at moſt but <hi>R.</hi> for <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>A.</hi> for <hi>R.</hi> and <hi>R. A.</hi> ſtill, which is much better than the contrary practice, of which ſome Authors have been guilty.</p>
            <p>As to the Reaſoning part, the Reader muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe my brevity, for in truth there is very little in it of that nature: however a few remarks may quicken and revive that faculty againſt the next turn. The Advocate owns it to be writ in anſwer to his Defence, <hi>ergo</hi> it Reflects upon the Nations Wiſdom. He expreſſes a reſentment at my Lord <hi>Ruſſels</hi> engaging in ſuch a weak and Criminal Enterpriſe, <hi>ergo</hi> he Reflects upon the Nations Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. He names the Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi> (though with the moſt tender Appellations that could be uſed) <hi>ergo</hi> he Reflects on that Lords memory. He vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicates the Indictment as good, <hi>ergo</hi> he juſtifies all the Proceedings in that Caſe. He argues that the Sentence was Legal upon ſuch a Verdict, <hi>ergo</hi> he is againſt the Reverſal. He puts a Caſe, offers a Point, and makes a Proof on't, <hi>ergo</hi> he is tranſcendently impudent. Theſe and ſuch like are the inferences, and do demerit a Laugh.</p>
            <p>As to Religion I ſee none in it, unleſs it be in the mention of the Deviliſh Powder Plot, which is ſtill as much to the purpoſe of his <hi>Reply,</hi> as the ſtory of Tranſmigration of Souls was to that of his <hi>Defence;</hi> only Meekneſs is tranſparent in his Stile Humility in the Title Page, and true Chriſtian Charity in his Menaces of an exception out of the Act of Indempnity which he repeats three or four times at leaſt, as if his whole intereſt were deſigned to promote it. The Gentlemans Danger is from publick and ſcandalous Actings in the Eye of the World: which were (ſays he) labouring to <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Government,</hi> every Man knows what ſort; laſhing the innocent with a <hi>bitter</hi> and <hi>ſharp Tongue,</hi> and <hi>inveigling</hi> of <hi>Juries</hi> with Rhetorical flouriſhes. Now to examin a little theſe three monſtrous Tranſgreſſions, let us go backwards; as to the laſt, a Duty can never be a Crime, every Servant owes Truth to his Maſter while ſuch: every Advocate is to do his utmoſt, and a failure in it had deſerved the worſt both of Names, and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which the <hi>Repliant</hi> could invent, or his intereſt procure. For all Mankind muſt agree, that the now Servants of the preſent Crown are obliged to do the like upon the like occaſion; if otherwiſe, the <hi>Jacobites</hi> ſide will be the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt. I will not reflect on the weakneſs of the Juries that were thus inveigled, if any ſuch there were, but rather ſuppoſe that the Oaths of Witneſſes, not the Pleading of Counſel did govern their Conſciences. As to the ſecond, that is falſe, and needs no other anſwer. As to the firſt, that Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans Honor and Merit afterwards, is as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable as his Fault at firſt, if it were any; but however he is likely to have abundance of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, in Deſert at leaſt, if not in Cenſure: for a Duke of <hi>York</hi>'s Creature, is certainly as Culpable
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105562:3"/>as a King <hi>James</hi>'s Servant. And <hi>Andrew Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels</hi> Characters in his growth of Popery, will be as true a Directory to decypher Criminals as the four Volumes of noted Tryals. And perhaps if the Ordinance of <hi>May</hi> 10. 1650. ſhould chance to be revived, danger and fear may ſeize other Men, as well as thoſe that lately ſerved paſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments; it is therefore thought adviſeable for all to ſit down quiet, and forgive and forget what is paſt, but ſerve God and their Majeſties for the future, and not belabour the Excepting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for if any ſhould be ſuch Fools, the Knaves will get the better on it, and the Righteous ſcarcely be ſaved. So much for Religion.</p>
            <p>Now for the Law if we can find it, But becauſe the <hi>Defender</hi> ſeems ſomewhat diſpleaſed at the repetition of that unhappy Lords name, whoſe Caſe gives occaſion for the preſent que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. Let us there put it like <hi>Mooters, John a Styles</hi> was Indicted for that he, at ſuch a time and place, did Compaſs to deprive his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Lord the King, that then was, of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal State<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to deſtroy his Life, and to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Government, and raiſe a Rebellion, and to fulfil that imagination, he, together with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, did then and there conſult, and agree to raiſe a Rebellion againſt the ſaid King, and to ſeize and deſtroy the Guards of the ſaid Kings Perſon, contrary to, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The queſtion was not whether <hi>J. S.</hi> was Guilty? Nor if the Witneſſes Swore falſe? Whether his Attainder were fit to be Reverſed; But the diſpute was whether that Indictment were Legal? Whether ſuppoſing <hi>J. S.</hi> to be found Guilty, the Court that pronounced the Sentence of Treaſon againſt him, ought to have Arreſted ſuch Judgment on the motion of <hi>J. S.</hi> that the Indictment was inſufficient? The Sheet argues that the Indictment was good, and conſequently the Sentence purſuant thereto was warrantable by the Laws of this Land. The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument ſeems founded both upon the Reaſon of Things, and the Authority of Preſidents.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The reaſon alledged was, that the laſt part, which in Lawyers terms is called an Overt Act, was a natural and genuine Senſe or Declaration, or Overt ſignification of the firſt part, which is an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſecret Thought, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Imagination and Compaſſing, which is the Treaſon Prohibited and Condemned. That the latter directly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentially tending, and conducing in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe and Reaſon of all Mankind (excepting the <hi>Defender,</hi> and two or three more) to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of the former, makes a good and ſufficient charge within the Stat. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. A Repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is tedious, and an Abridgment is ſcarcely poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, the whole Sheet being but a Breviate, I ſhall therefore refer you thereto.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Authorities there urged, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Opinions of Judges and other Lawyers, or Precedents of Indictments of the like, or the ſame nature, from which the Legality of this may be juſtly concluded. The ſubſtance of them on the whole matter is, that Overt Acts to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the King, or deſpoil him of his Regal Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, or take him by Force or ſtrong Hand, or to Impriſon his Perſon, till he yields to the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mands of thoſe who practiſe ſuch endeavours, are ſufficient Overt Acts to prove the Compaſſing and Imagination of his Death. That Levying War, cauſing an Inſurrection, promoting an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion, nay that Conſults, Conſpiracies, Practices, Advices, Letters, Perſuaſions, and other Motives, and preparations to an Inſurrection, or Invaſion, though none ſucceed, have been held Overt Acts of Imagining the Kings Death. I will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat the Caſes but as occaſion offers from the other ſide.</p>
            <p>The Objections there mentioned and anſwered from the Penning of the Statute, are too tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial to deſerve a remembrance, nor would they have ever been thought otherwiſe, but that <hi>J. S.</hi> was a Noble Perſon, and the <hi>Defender</hi> a great Man, and the Prefacer thought ſo too, either by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or others. Theſe and ſuch like ingredients have made ſome ſemblance of difficulty: and in truth, had there been a real doubt in the Caſe, the Author of the <hi>Remarks</hi> on that Tryal, who wanted neither Senſe nor Will to Cenſure it, had his Opinion ſo inclined, I ſay he would certainly have faln foul on it in thoſe invidious Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his upon the late Times. He quarrels with the Legallity of the Jurors. The <hi>Defender</hi> with that of the Indictment, and both with the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. The Author of the Sheet differs from them in the two firſt, but agrees with them in the laſt, that Teſtimony delivered for fear of Life, or hopes of Pardon, or other Reward, is hardly Creditable; but that is not the Point. Let us ſee if the <hi>Repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> doth overthrow the Charge as inſufficient, and for my part I cannot find a Line of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in it, but only it is naught becauſe it is naught. The Conſulting, and Concluding to make an Inſurrection and Rebellion, and ſeize the Kings Guards, is not a Declaration of the Parties compaſſing the King's Depoſal or Death, and why? Becauſe Conſpiring to Levy War is not a Levying War, and Levying War is a diſtinct Treaſon; this is the ſubſtance of the tenth Page, if I can read: The Sheet ſaid and truly, That Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying War it ſelf might be alledg'd as an Overt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act of the Compaſſing, and hath been ſo frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and meeting and agreeing to rebel and ſeize the Guards, hath a direct tendency to promote a Demiſe of the King either natural or civil, and therefore might as well be alledged an Overt-act as moſt things whatſoever.</p>
            <p>I had almoſt forgot one Clauſe, and that is, the unneceſſarineſs of making 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. if it ſhould be as the Advocate argues; I ſuppoſe he means the firſt Paragraph, for the ſecond is agreed to be introductive of a new Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the firſt is only a Paraphraſe upon the 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. It is thus. <hi rend="blackletterType">That if any Perſon or Perſons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, ſhall within the Realm, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, compaſs, imagin, invent, deviſe, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend death or deſtruction, or any bodily harm tending to death or deſtruction, maim or wounding, impriſonment, or reſtraint
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105562:3"/>of the perſon of our Sovereign Lord the King, or to deprive or depoſe him from the ſtyle, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, or kingly name of the imperial Crown of this Realm, or of any other his Majeſties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions or Countries, or to levy war againſt his Majeſty within this Realm or without, or to move or ſtir any Foreigner or Strangers with force to invade this Realm, or any other his Majeſties Dominions and Countries being under his obeyſance, and ſuch compaſſings, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, inventions, devices, or intentions, or any of them ſhall expreſs, utter, or declare, by any printing, writing, preaching, or malicious adviſed ſpeaking, being legally convicted thereof, by the Oaths of two lawful and credible Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes vpon Tryal, or otherwiſe convicted or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted by due courſe of Law; then every ſuch,</hi> &amp;c. <hi rend="blackletterType">ſhall,</hi> &amp;c. Now what is all this but a confirmation of the old Statute inwords at length; which was agreed to be ſo in the Houſe of Commons, 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> 2. when a motion was made to renew that Law, the Lawyers Anſwer was, that the 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. did the ſame thing, and a Man may boldly ſay it, that here's nothing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd Treaſon, but what had been adjudg'd ſo before, and Attainders and Executions had purſuant to it: The Sheet mentions Caſes enough and to the purpoſe, tho ſome think otherwiſe; but I'll not repeat them:</p>
            <p>In the 11th. page the Reader is referr'd to the juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in the half ſheet; and therefore let's examin that a little; a third part of it is ſpent upon the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but that is not within my Province, which is only to vindicate the Vindication: As to the reſt, the force of it, if any, ſeems only to be founded on his firſt Aſſertion, the conſpiring to do a thing is not the doing a thing, and he quotes two great Mens Names for it, I would have agreed that, tho he had ſpar'd the Authority to juſtifie it; but this is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently anſwered in the Sheet: He offers an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the late Statutes declaring Treaſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were temporary, but I anſwer as the Sheet doth, they were in affirmance of the old Law, and I can ſhew him three or four temporary, and an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred other Acts of Parliament that are ſo, and therefore that is no Argument at all; but I am, as the Party I juſtifie was, confin'd to a Sheet, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enlarge.</p>
            <p>He lays down a Rule for conſtruction of Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, that a thing particulariz'd in one part is not to be conſtrued within the general words of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part, but that Rule hath near fourſcore Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Books; beſides, it come not to this Caſe, for here's compaſſing the King's Death made Treaſon, and declar'd by Overt-act then levying War is made Treaſon: Now ſays the Repliant, nothing can be an Overt-act of and conduce to promote and accompliſh the firſt, that doth any ways concern the latter, I ſay it is a <hi>non ſequitur;</hi> for there are ſeveral Inſtances mentioned in the Sheet, which reſpect the levying War, and yet are a genuine evidence of the intention and compaſſing; and if ſo, the Judges who have rul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch Indictments to be good, did neither aſſume an arbitrary Power, nor tranſgreſs any Rule of Law, as the half Sheet inſinuates.</p>
            <p>Then the Lord <hi>Cobham</hi>'s Caſe is endeavoured to be anſwerd, by a Wonder that Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> late Lord Chief Juſtice and then Sheriff, ſhould differ from Mr. Attorny <hi>Coke;</hi> for we know his thoughts in Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi>'s time and his Speeches in <hi>Car.</hi> I. his time; they are as different each from the other as the times were; and in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, that Gentleman hath had more followers than precedents; but the Query is, What is law.</p>
            <p>Then Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi>'s Caſe is endeavoured to be anſwered by this that <hi>Syderfin</hi> mentions not the Overt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act in the Indictment, but he doth ſay the Treaſon al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd was a compaſſing the King's Death, and every Man knows what Sir <hi>Hen. Vane</hi> did to accompliſh that, he neither ſign'd the Warrant to execute that Murder, nor was he actually concern'd in it; the Juſtifier ſays he does not remember it printed any where but in <hi>Syderfin</hi>'s Reports; for the refreſhment of his Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry I'll tell him of another Book where it is, and that's <hi>Keble</hi>'s Firſt Volume of Reports, 304. and there the Indictment is ſaid to be for Compaſſing the King's Death, and endeavouring to accompliſh the Treaſon by Changing and Uſurping the Government, and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying War, which Caſe doth directly overthrow all the Defenders, Juſtifiers and Repliants Arguments from the diſtinctneſs or difference of the ſort of Treaſon.</p>
            <p>Then for Dr. <hi>Story</hi>'s Caſe, he ſays 'tis hard to juſtifie it for Law; whereas there are above forty places in our printed Law Books where 'tis cited and agreed to be Law: Now 'tis pretty odd, that a Caſe ſo reſolved and ſo ratified, ſhould one Hundred and eighteen Years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, be arraigned in print, for 'twas <hi>Hill.</hi> 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> if any thing be Law, that is ſo, and not diſtinguiſhable from this Caſe in queſtion, but that the Evidence was different, which the Juſtifier would make a reaſon to invalidate this Indictment; the Logick of it paſſeth all Underſtanding; beſides, 'tis very obſervable, that the Benches were fill'd both with Learning and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity in 1571. and 1662. neither of thoſe times were Tory or Popiſh; and in <hi>Dyer</hi> 298. the reaſon given was, that it could not tend but to the great peril of the King's Perſon, and therefore an attempt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote ſuch Invaſion, tho none followed, was adjudg'd as aforeſaid: In 2. <hi>Anderſon pl.</hi> 2. <hi>fo.</hi> 5. <hi>Grant</hi>'s Caſe 'twas held, that when any perſon intendeth or contriveth to levy War for a thing which the Queen by her Law or Juſtice ought or may do in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as Queen, it's not material whether they intend any hurt to her Perſon; but if they intend to levy War againſt the Office and Authority of the Queen, that's enough, and that reſolution overthrows the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiers Notion, that <hi>J. S.</hi> his Deſign was only to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Laws, tho the 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> alſo was then in force, it's a good Argument to anſwer that pretence:</p>
            <p>Now I have repeated and obſerved all the Replication or Juſtification offers in anſwer to my Friend's Sheet, the Reader may perhaps expect ſome new Matter, not ſo much for confirmation, as to give occaſion for a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther further defence. In Sir <hi>Fr. Moor</hi>'s <hi>Rep. fol</hi> 621. <hi>pl.</hi> 849 on the Tryals of the Earls of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampton</hi> before the then High Steward, the Juſtices did there reſolve, that when the Queen ſent to the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> the Keeper of her Great Seal, and others, with a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105562:4"/>Command to him to diſperſe the Perſons armed which he had in his Houſe, and to come to her, and he did refuſe to do ſo, and continued the Armour and armed Perſons in his Houſe, that this was Treaſon; and they did alſo reſolve, that when he went with a Troop of Captains and others from his Houſe to the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and there prayed Aid of the Citizens to aſſiſt him in defence of his Life, and to go with him to Court that he might get into the Queens preſence, that he might be ſufficiently powerful to remove from her his Enemies who were there attendant, that this was High Treaſon, becauſe it tended to a Force on the Queen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I make no inference, let the Reader do that; 'tis plain that an actual mental intention of hurt is not material in the one Caſe or the other. As the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Caſe is related by <hi>Cambden</hi> in his Hiſtory of Q <hi>Eliz.</hi> 163. the Treaſon which the Duke confeſſed, was a Plot to ſeize upon the Tower of <hi>London</hi> and deliver the Queen of Scots, and that's all.</p>
            <p>There's nothing remains in doubt, but the legality or illegality of the King's keeping Guards for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his Perſon; they ſay the Law takes care of him, and therefore he is to take none of himſelf, and that the Judges are his Guards, and therefore he needs no other, that <hi>Hen.</hi> VII. was the firſt King who had any other. But let us reaſon a little; Can it be ſuppoſed, that he ſhould be ſo ſacred in his Perſon, ſo great in his Power, and of ſuch Authority as to make War or Peace abroad, and raiſe Forces and ſuppreſs them at home, as the Danger or Defence of his Realm ſhould require, and not be able to provide for his own perſonal Safety <hi>de preſenti,</hi> can he only puniſh by his Judges afterwards, or prohibit by Proclamation before, but not defend himſelf for the preſent? Is it ſenſe to ſuppoſe it? The Kings of <hi>England</hi> might have, and actually had Soldiers or Guards (call them what you will) even in times of Peace, and long before <hi>Hen.</hi> VII. as well as continually ſince; I may be ſo bold as to defie any man to ſhew me the Year, the Month, the Week, or the Day, ſince the Conqueſt by <hi>William</hi> I. that <hi>England</hi> was without armed Men actual upon Duty in ſome part or other of the Nation. This Sheet is not intended for a ſtudied Argument on this Subject; and perhaps it would be difficult to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie a ſtanding Army as warrantable, when there's no occaſion for it; but to ſay he can't by force even by force provide for his own perſonal ſafety, when he apprehends it in danger, as every Engliſh King hath continual reaſon to do, eſpecially if ſome Mens Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine prevail, it may be modeſtly affirmed unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: Hath not every Subject power to keep Arms as well as Servants in his Houſe for defence of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Is not his Manſion called his Caſtle? And yet the Law protects him too by Prohibitions <hi>à parte ante</hi> and Puniſhments <hi>ex parte poſt:</hi> There are many Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nures in <hi>England</hi> which oblige to the annual payment of certain Sums towards Soldiers Wages for Defence of the King and Kingdom; there are others oblige to the annual finding certain quantities of Grain in kind for the ſupplying the King's Caſtles and Garriſons, as well as Houſhold; which being annual, do demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the lawfulneſs of their continuance, even in times of Peace, and their being immemorial do conclude a Common Law right in the Kings of <hi>England</hi> to have thoſe Occaſions, as they do conclude him a right to have them ſupplied by ſuch like Services: Nay Grand Serjeantry is either by Services of attendance on the King's Perſon in time of Peace, or for Military Aids, in time of War. The Crown may raiſe Forces by Commiſſion or of the Militia to ſuppreſs Inſurrections in caſe the Civil Power of the Sheriff is not ſufficient or ineffectual: The Kings of <hi>England</hi> have the ſole Power and Force of the Nation, Complaints have been in Parliament againſt Billeting Soldiers contrary to the Will of the Hoſts, but never for maintaining a Guard for their own Perſon at their own charge; Complaints have been of a Standing Army, but never of a ſelect company for his perſonal preſervation; a Terror to the People may as well be pretended from his Coachmen, Footmen, or Grooms, if their Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers be great; beſides, for a competent Power in Arms he always may have occaſion, when his Subjects know nothing on't; 'tis his Province to foreſee and prevent as well as ſuppreſs and puniſh domeſtick Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, and the buſineſs of War is ſeparately his Office, and that excluſive of his Subjects any otherwiſe than as they are bound to obey and fight, or deſired to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with Aids and Subſidies, and for this to avoid a numerous Volume of Citations, I'll name one notable Roll or two, <hi>in Parliament.</hi> 6. <hi>Ric.</hi> II. <hi>Mem.</hi> 9. the manner and way of the proſecution of a War being given in charge to the Commons to adviſe upon, they anſwered, that this <hi>nec doit nec ſolayt</hi> appertain <hi>al eux mes al Roy,</hi> and ſo they did, 31 <hi>Edward</hi> III. <hi>Parte. prim. n.</hi> 11. &amp; 21 <hi>Edward</hi> III. <hi>n.</hi> 5. it's true in 5 <hi>Edward</hi> II. <hi>n.</hi> 4. Ordinances were made, that the King without the aſſent of his Barons could not make Wars, but thoſe were repealed and dampned. 15 <hi>Edw.</hi> II. <hi>Parl. Rot. m.</hi> 13. becauſe prejudicial to the Royal Power of a King, and this is ſufficiently affirmed by the Act concerning the Militia in <hi>Carol.</hi> II. his time. It is well known in what time <hi>Bryan</hi> Chief Juſtice ſaid, that if all the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> ſhould war with the Subjects of anothers Kingdom, that this is no War, unleſs the King denounces it: It ſuffices for my friend's Point, that the King may lawfully have armed Men or Guards, when himſelf judges his Perſon or People to be in danger, or ſtand in need of them: And that he may, when reaſons of State will not admit their publication to the World; but however ſome ſtanding Force the Crown ever had and ever will have, tho not always to ſuch a degree as ſhall be burdenſom or oppreſſive; and our old Law Books ſay that Arms as well as Laws are neceſſary for the Prince, not only in but againſt the times of neceſſity, I mean War or Tumult; beſides in <hi>Bracton lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>de Corona,</hi> 'tis ſaid, that <hi>crimen leſae majeſtatis</hi> is the greateſt Crime be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the greatneſs of the Perſon againſt whom 'tis committed; his deſcription of it is, <hi>preſumptio contra perſonam ipſius Regis;</hi> then when he particularizes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105562:4"/>the ſeveral ſorts of Treaſon, the firſt which he names is, <hi>Si quis auſu temerario machinatus ſit in (i. e.</hi> towards) <hi>mortem domini Regis, vel aliquid egerit vel agi procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit ad ſeditionem Domini Regis vel exercitus ſui, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet id quod in voluntate habuerit non perduxerit ad effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum.</hi> I'll make no Inference, there needs no Paraphraſe, the words are plain; an Act tending to the deſtruction of the King's <hi>Hoſt</hi> is High Treaſon againſt his <hi>Perſon; agere ad ſeditionem exercitus regis eſt preſumptio contra perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Regis, &amp; preſumptio contra perſonam Regis eſt cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men leſae Majeſtatis:</hi> Now can <hi>Bracton</hi> be thought to ſpeak only of Treaſons in time of War, <hi>Glanvill. lib.</hi> 14. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>crimen leſae Majeſtatis dicitur de ſeditione Domini Regis vel regni vel exercitus:</hi> and <hi>Fleta lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>De ſeductione exercitus ſui: &amp; cap.</hi> 21. the ſame words, <hi>ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem ejus vel exercitus ſui;</hi> this was the ſenſe of the old Law, and is very appoſitely applicable to the Caſe in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, as I could eaſily ſhew, would my Paper bear it. There is one thing which I had quite forgot, and that is, that the Inſtrument of Grievances which the Prudence of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament hath provided, complains of a <hi>Standing Army;</hi> the Anſwer is eaſie, 'tis not of <hi>Perſonal Guards;</hi> and the wiſe enquiry of the Houſe of Commons into the <hi>quantum</hi> requiſite to maintain ſuch and ſuch Forces during the preſent occaſion, and of the Expences of the Crown in Houſhold, Courts, Guards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> afterwards, do plainly ſhew, that that was not the intended Grievance: Now to ſum up what is not anſwered at all or endeavoured to be ſo; by the Defender, nothing is ſaid to the reaſon of the thing, or the neceſſity and nature of an Overt-act, to the opinion of <hi>Coke</hi> in theplaces cited, to the Caſe of Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> the Caſe of the Cardinal, the Caſe of Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> the Caſe of <hi>Conſtable,</hi> the Caſe of <hi>Owen,</hi> the Caſe of <hi>Burton,</hi> the Caſes of <hi>Sparhauke, Awater,</hi> and <hi>Heber,</hi> the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt Sir <hi>Willam Aſhton, Germain</hi> and <hi>Taylor,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Burdett, Collingbourne,</hi> and <hi>Colledge,</hi> nor to the Opinion of the Judges in the Lord <hi>Stafford</hi>'s Caſe, as if 'twere all impertinent, but the Reader is Judge if it be ſo.</p>
            <p>Now for the Prefacer, I'll be as ſhort upon him as he was upon my Friend; he ſaid that the Sheet needed a Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and I have given it one, and if this needs another, I hope the Crown will find ſome Friend to write a Third; he ſeems ſo us'd to the word <hi>Libel,</hi> that he cannot forbear calling it an <hi>infamous</hi> one; he ſays it has not one true ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial word in it, I'll remember him of one, that mocking is catching in the Proverb, that is, <hi>A Grumbletonian in the Stirrup generally proves a Tyrant — in the Saddle;</hi> that's enough for him to remember: If he wants any more truth, and that he may not ſay this hath none in't, Treaſons are eaſier committed than diſtinguiſh'd, by ſome Men eſpecially, and the reaſon why I ſay this, is becauſe of his Octavo Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face when he is grumbling ſtill, for I always thought that he had ſmarted too much for Libelling on Miniſters of State and Male-Adminiſtrations, to venture again; but when a Prieſt meddles with Law, he is like an Apothecary at Politicks, he generally runs himſelf into a Nooze, for he'll never leave off till he's advanced one way or another. To conclude, the deſign of the Sheet was to juſtifie the Prerogative of the King and Queen, and the Rights of their Crown, and the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican is angry, that either ſhould have any, and from thence flames the Paſſion; nay, rather than it ſhould be allowed, they'll attempt another Change, from which good Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.2.</p>
            <p>During the compoſure of the Premiſes, News was brought me that another Pen had been procured to attack the Vindication, <hi>viz.</hi> The Author that runs a muck at all Mankind, except his own Patroons: A deſerved and full remark upon ſo voluminous a Book, is not here to be expected, however, this Appendix may ſerve for an Advertiſement to the World, that the new Repliant is in ſeveral particulars obliged to Solicitor <hi>Coke,</hi> and the other Regicides defence on their Tryals for much of his Materials, time is wanting to ſhew the Parallel, at preſent 'tis fit to be obſerved, that hisblind ſide alſo is apparent, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly capable of a ſufficient Anſwer, and to give my Reader a Specimen thereof. I'll take notice of a few (amongſt many) Miſtakes both in Fact and Law, which he hath wilfully committed; In the firſt Page he ſays, That to juſtifie what hath been taken ill, accuſes the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Injuſtice; which is falſe. In Page 2. he ſays, That the Vindication ventures on a Point of Law which it pretends is the reſult of the Evidence given; there's no ſuch pretence in the whole Paper, the only Debate was upon the Indictment: He ſays in the ſame Page, that it's ſaid his Relations were pleaſed with the juſtneſs of the Tryal; it only ſays, His Relations were pleaſed, and his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies angry with thoſe who then ſate upon the Bench, and that's true; for ſome of his Relations cannot deny it, the Fact is ſo well known: The laſt line of Page 3. and firſt of the next are alſo falſe; for 'twas neither written, perus'd, nor approv'd by any of his pretended Criminals: I believe they thought the Point too clear to need a Vindication; but this is juſt like his wonted poſitiveneſs in his Remarks; where for inſtance he ſays, That one of the Judgments he cavils at was the firſt that was ever given without Argument or Reaſons delivered in Court, which is alſo falſe; for in <hi>Plowden</hi>'s Comment. 459. In Sir <hi>Tho. Wroth</hi>'s Caſe, the Author takes expreſs notice, that the reaſons of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were not diſcloſed when the ſame was pronounc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and Fifty other Caſes I could name him of the ſame, but one Inſtance is enough to falſifie a general indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Poſition, tho there are ſeveral more even in that very Book.</p>
            <p>But to run over his Volume, Pag 2. is only a farther ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous Reflection to vindicate his own Remarks, and an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent bombaſt of words on the Phraſe of Engliſh proced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: The 3. P. aſſigns four Reaſons of Printing, the two laſt are applicable to himſelf only, and he thinks ſo of the fourth, or elſe his Story is fooliſh like — In the 4. P. he boulſters up himſelf in his Railery, by reſorting to his refuge of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Authority that reverſed the Judgment, which all Men agree to be juſt, but it was not becauſe the Recorder did not arreſt the Judgment on that trivial Exception to the Indictment, but becauſe the Proſecution was ſuppoſed malicious, and the Evidence ſuppoſed falſe or deficient, or both.</p>
            <p>The 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, and 10th. Pages are all impertinent to the Point in queſtion, and contain nothing but a Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his juſtly condemned Clamour in his former Book; concerning which, I'll boldly ſay it, in ſeventeen Points of twenty he is out in his Law; if 'twere convenient to pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſh the proof on't, I could make it plain. His deſign is to ſhew in thoſe Pages his Wit and Fancy, more than Candor or Law; for my part. I am of his Friends mind that he comes not ſhort of the old Obſervator for managing a Dialogue:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105562:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>But all this is not to the purpoſe, he is not come at it yet, he 12. page ſavours of the ſame Kidney, the 13. and 14. are no better: there he vents his Gall, and that in Ribal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry; no ſofter a name than Tools can be afforded to Men of Worth and Honor: if himſelf be one, as ſome ſuppoſe him, I am ſure it is not to the preſent Government, for he plainly condemns it, and declares the People, <hi>i. e.</hi> his ſort of them, unſatified with it, for its ſparingneſs in vengeance, and it is becauſe others are not puniſhed for maintaining the Law, and themſelves not preferred for Arraigning it: ſome Men know my meaning. He ſays he is only for mumbling of Judges and Counſel, <hi>Cauſa patet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I muſt tell him two things. 1. The inclinations of <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> and the Laws of the Land, will never quadrate with a Common-wealth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His ſuppoſed Criminals do not depend on their Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, but the Law, which ought, and will juſtifie them; if it doth not pleaſe, let it be changed by Parliament, or if the Author thinks that a tedious way, let us burn all our Law Books at once, and then perhaps his <hi>Remarks</hi> and <hi>Reply</hi> will be thought to be Reaſon, and himſelf the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and only Lawyer in the Realm; but till then, he muſt give others leave to know, and to ſay that they know, he is miſtaken: for Reſolutions, and Opinions, purſuant, and agreeable to the Opinions, and Rules of former Ages, I mean frequent and repeated Preſidents, approved by the Lawyers of the Age that uſed them. I ſay theſe will be Law to the end of the World, unleſs altered by new Statutes.</p>
            <p>And now we are come to debate the Queſtion, all that is paſt is upon the Times, and not the Point. In page 18. is his Reaſoning part, which is no more than was ſaid before in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To redargue him I muſt repeat; if therefore he will obſerve what is ſaid by the Sheet pag 22. I will ſay no more on't, but ſubmit to the Judgment of the Reader, he ſays the inferences are Ridiculous, I ſay they are Rational and Genuine: the ſingle iſſue is, if his, or my friends Arguments are the moſt Logical and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, let the Reader judg.</p>
            <p>Now for Authority, Let us ſee if he urges any on his ſide, or anſwers that on the other. He admires (pag. 24) at the aſſurance of the Sheet Author, and others admire at his. He ſays the Parliament had often adjudged it, but none can ſhew any Judgment in the Houſe of Lords, or Vote of the Commons Houſe to that purpoſe. I have ſhewn the Senſe of the preſent Parliament in the Point of Guards, and his temporary Laws are already anſwered; nor would any M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n but he, and one more, pretend that they are Judgments in the Caſe. Surely it will not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that his Caſe of the Earl of <hi>Northumberlands</hi> in <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. time, is any thing to the purpoſe: Nor is it any Argument to ſay, no King of <hi>England</hi> was ever killed for want of Guards.</p>
            <p>Now for Caſes page 26. He ſaith that in the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi>'s Caſe there was an actual War Levyed, and that as I ſaid before, deſtroys the Argument from the different ſorts of Treaſon. As to Cardinal <hi>Pool</hi>'s Caſe, he only ſays there was another Statute in force then, but no Record or Hiſtory ſays that he was indicted on any other then the 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. As to Dr. <hi>Story</hi>'s Caſe, he tells a long Tale out of <hi>Camden</hi> about the Fact, but anſwers not one word to the Indictment, whatſoever the Evidence was, the Indictment was as the Sheet alledges, and that is enough.</p>
            <p>His anſwer to <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Caſe is that, that things hapning afterwards proved more, but the Evidence was no more than what my Friend alledges. As to Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi>'s Caſe, his anſwer is, his own hearſay of what was proved, but the Judgment he never peruſed, <hi>argued like a Lawyer.</hi> As to <hi>Conſtable</hi>'s Caſe and the reſt, he gives no anſwer, but only that a repetition of a number of Caſes makes a mutter and a noiſe, and ſo it does when they Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern and Rule the matter in queſtion, and are not anſwered. <hi>Owen</hi>'s Caſe he ſays the Author preſſes it ſtrangely and that is all. He ſays the Caſes of <hi>Burton,</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk, Awater, Heber,</hi> and <hi>Crohagn,</hi> are not to the purpoſe, let the Reader judg if they are not pertinent: As to the Opinion of the Judges in the Lord <hi>Stafford</hi>'s Caſe, he doth not mention it, but ſays the reviving that Caſe might have been ſpared, and that is all, a pretty anſwer; as to <hi>Colledg</hi>'s Caſe, he talks of a proof of a ſelf Defence, but nothing to the Point it was urged for. As to the Caſes of Lord <hi>Cobham, Gray,</hi> and <hi>Rawleigh,</hi> in 32. 33, 34, 55. pag. Setting aſide his ſcandalous Invectives and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon thoſe Times, Miniſters, and Governments, he no ways attempts to anſwer the Argument drawn from them, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Charge was the ſame as in the Caſe in Diſpute.</p>
            <p>Now do I appeal to any Man of Senſe and Reaſon that will Read and Think cloſely, if the <hi>Repliant</hi> hath offered any one Argument more than the Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Caſe, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and Juſtification had alledged. If he hath ſhewn any one Judgment where ſuch Indictment was reſolved naught. If he hath given any anſwer to Dr. <hi>Story</hi>'s, <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingborn</hi>'s, Sir <hi>William Aſhton</hi>'s, <hi>Burdet</hi>'s, and Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi>'s Indictment, in ſhort if he hath anſwered any two of the Caſes cited: or if he hath done any thing but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on paſt and late times, and if the Indictment re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main not good both for matter and form, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all theſe pretended Replies. Upon the whole matter, I deſire the Reader to peruſe the Books cited, and to judg if there be not preſidents enough unanſwered to juſtifie the Indictment in queſtion, and that the Recorder gave a good Judgment upon the Verdict that affirmed its truth; <hi>quod fuit Probandum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, Since the <hi>Repliant</hi> is in love with <hi>Horace,</hi> I would adviſe him to conſider one hint of his</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>—Forum, putealque Libonis</l>
                  <l>Mandabo ſiccis.—</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hor.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
